- My name is Ram Subramanian.
I'm the Vice President for Instruction at De Anza College,
and I'm the moderator for this panel this afternoon.
Just a little setup for our panel.
As we know, cybersecurity
is one of the fastest growing fields in our economy today,
but it's also one that is most challenged in the workforce.
We just don't seem to have enough qualified
members within the workforce in cybersecurity yet.
We have lots of threats
that are constantly growing in scale and sophistication,
more importantly.
So, we at least, I'm kind of, somewhat biased,
think of ourselves in the community colleges
as playing a pivotal role in generating this talent pipeline
for the future of cybersecurity ecosystem.
So we hope we are providing
affordable and accessible education,
and we have, we hope to build pathways
that connect our students to meaningful careers.
But our success depends on strong partnerships
between the industry, the government,
and other statewide initiatives.
And so we are here to learn from our panel
about how we bridge those gaps between the industry
and also the higher education system.
So please join me in welcoming our panelists.
We have five of them here today.
David Doyle, Ron Sha, Hsiawen Hull, Aaron Wurthmann,
and Blake Williams.
And I'm gonna have them introduce themselves to you.
So we'll start with David first.
- Hi, can you hear me?
Good morning, afternoon, I guess, sorry. My name is David.
I am former CISO,
currently providing fractional CISO services.
Been in the cyber space for about 30 years or so
in a lot of capacities.
Pretty much everything except pharmaceutical,
although I like to try and get credit,
my partner's on the animal pharmaceutical side,
so, yeah, you know, it's been a really interesting,
I think, growth of security.
And, at former life, I actually worked
for a community college workforce development program
providing services to both DOD
as well as some of our friends at the school level,
so a lot of experience over the years.
Currently also providing some mentorship
for undergrad capstone private, I'm sorry, program,
as well as a grad program for KSU in Georgia.
- Hi, my name is Ron Sha.
And, so I have been working in the industry
before start teaching back in 2011, or, yeah, 2011.
So before that I was working at the industry
in various high tech companies,
and as a CIO of startup,
medium size and large size companies.
And so once I started teaching and not only,
and I also helped develop a various
information technology curriculums.
And in 2019, I also that only college program
to be designated by NSA as,
you know, the National Center of Academic Excellence
in cybersecurity education.
So the key sense is more of how can we continue
to work with the industry, with our peers,
and so, getting involved
in the overall cybersecurity education.
- Thank you, Ron.
- Oh, looks like my mic is on.
I'm only one with a dedicated mic, so take that you guys.
Aaron Wurthmann,
about 25 years of IT and security experience
primarily at startups.
Each one of those startups
tends to get acquired by a much larger company.
Companies of note would be Neustar, Adobe,
small company called Adobe, et cetera.
I've also worked in retail at Albertsons
where I was the head of digital security.
Digital security at Albertsons looks something like
all the data that's collected on shoppers,
all the web app, the mobile app,
all of those sort of things.
We see that we saw that as a $10 billion asset.
So my job was to secure all of those.
These days I work with startups and medium sized companies
that securing their companies, their infrastructure,
as a advisory CISO at 909 Cyber.
I am also on the board of the CIO scholarship fund
with my partner Hiran.
And I'm on the board of the ISSA,
which is a organization whose purpose is to educate students
and anyone who's interested in cybersecurity.
- All right. My name's Hsiawen Hull.
I'm the executive director
of infrastructure and information security
at College of the Canyons.
In addition to that, I'm also the CSO
for the CCC Security Center,
which is actually a grant funded program
from the Chancellor's office where we are providing,
you know, insight and services
to secure all the community colleges in California.
I've been in the system specifically for 27 years.
I've taught in CTE programs including a plus certification.
And actually at the high school level,
I built the local high school's animal science program.
You can ask me about that later.
So I've been, I think I've touched or taught
or worked in pretty much every area of IT
within the community college system.
And so, you know, this place really,
I live and sleep, breathe community colleges,
so, happy to be here.
- Welcome panelists. So as you see,
we have two members from the community colleges
and two industry partners.
And I had a set of questions,
which they've already seen before,
but I'm gonna go from the middle
of my set of questions that I have here,
which is, it's not lost on me that the panel and myself,
all included, identify as males.
So, I want to know,
how can we ensure that underrepresented students,
including women and students of color,
see cybersecurity as a viable career path
that they have access to training opportunities.
Do you want to speak to that? Any of you?
- Well, I dedicated mic, so, I'm the first.
Yeah, so first I'd say I'm a person,
I'm someone who identifies as a person of color,
despite my Anglo last name, don't let that fool you.
But more specifically on women in cyber,
you know, I think first it comes with awareness,
you pointed it out,
but I think next, after awareness is acknowledgement.
We don't do that enough
or we don't give enough opportunity.
On one of the boards that I'm on,
we had to actively seek a woman for that board.
That was intentional, it was purposeful.
And it, that tends to happen more and more.
I'm glad it happens,
but, I think it's, it starts with awareness
and it starts with acknowledging,
- Go ahead.
- Yeah, so I agree with Aaron.
I think awareness early on is very important.
And so one of the things we have done
is we have invited woman as a guest speakers
or people with color as a guest speakers.
And then we also involved with like girls code club as well.
And we actively sometime go to the high school
to really to show that,
you know, especially if you bring a woman
or a person with color so they can see themselves.
Yeah, I can do that as well.
- Okay, alright.
- I think, I mean, step one for me
starts with providing opportunities.
I think the big piece of,
and I think we'll get to this later in cyber, cyber,
there's a lot of gatekeeping
and a lot of elitism within this field.
And because of that, I think that tends to shy folks away.
I think the last two years, of going on two years,
I put together programs for internships.
When we focus on soliciting those interns,
my goal is always even numbers, right?
So I'll always, I tell my female interns this all the time
is I take two females to males,
and every single time it's easier to find my females.
For some reason, their resumes were better,
their experience aligns to what I've asked,
all of those things.
But generally they're not given those opportunities
because for whatever reason,
whether the opportunity was never presented to them
or that they've never taken advantage of it.
By creating, I think, spaces
where students know that they have an opportunity
to come in, whether they are female, male, of color,
you know, that's really step one.
Providing support to organizations
that actually focus on providing those opportunities,
also, especially inward reaching.
We have multiple programs
within our community college systems
that focus on our dreamers, our our students of color.
Making sure that as a person in the field that's,
providing those opportunities,
making sure I'm at those meetings, talking to those people,
letting them know that, that, hey, I'm here.
I know, I know I'm limited, I can only do so much,
but, at least if nothing else.
Know that there's an opportunity there.
And I think that's really the hard part
is making sure that people in the field
are stepping into those spaces where we're not,
and then providing those opportunities. Thank you.
- Yeah, just to add.
I think too, it's creating the culture
within the organization, right?
Or amplifying the culture
that already exists in the organization.
A lot of times that part tends to get missed.
And so, you're not building that groundswell
within organization or we're supporting that,
making that an important factor and component
that I think that it really adds some unnecessary obstacles,
and in some ways dissuades people from wanting to,
to kind of be a continued part of that.
But then I'll, I would also add, you know, getting out
and working with the community groups
that are trying to implement that,
use that as a force multiplier.
- Thank you. Yeah, I heard gatekeeping and elitism
from pretty much all of you, and I think that is something
that we all need to be actively paying attention to.
So, going back to the top of my questions here.
So we often hear about the cybersecurity talent shortage.
And from your perspective,
where are the biggest gaps right now
and how are colleges and industry working together
to address these gaps?
- Well, we saw the emerging technologies
and so the skillset of our workforce ever changes.
So the gap is evident getting bigger and bigger
because our, you know, the educational institution has,
some of that has now been kept up.
And also, even in the general populations,
especially in the school,
some of the students has not even been taught or,
about cybersecurity until they go to college
or some of them even after the college as well.
So, one of the key senses
is more of how can you make the awareness
and also people view this is a career or a area
they should get into.
Especially right now, as we all know,
cybersecurity is just not only IT type things,
it affect every industry, right?
Whether you're business, healthcare,
you know, all different kind of things.
So and not only,
and I also try to work with a different department.
So they're asking to, you know, to add some topics,
you know, on SOCs, right?
Or HIPAA in a different department.
And also some of the fundamental cybersecurity skillset.
So one of the challenges, I believe, even for the student,
sometimes it is hard,
even though they say there's tons of job out there.
Well, yes, there is.
But it's very hard for community college student who,
because they don't have the job related experience
and the company all the time want to have people
with some kind of experience, right?
So that is also a challenge. And how can we get around that?
How can we help our student
so that they can get a little head start?
And, so that's the reason, like for myself and Aaron,
you know, we know each other for a long time.
We are working with industry professionals and,
so that we provide the opportunity
for student for internship, mentoring
as some my colleague was saying.
So, you know,
you know, I think that those things all added up together.
- Yeah, so, what I see a lot of our,
our folks that have solid skill sets
they don't know how to apply those skill sets
or where to apply those skill sets at.
It's one of the reasons why I'm so big into community
and I'm a part of three or four different communities.
What I'd like to see is where are more students
applying themselves to more communities?
'Cause that's where the jobs are at, right?
We're far removed from the time
when you could just apply to a job
and you would get an interview.
Those days are gone.
Every job that anybody applies to, myself,
anybody on this panel any and you apply to,
there are gonna be 300, 400, 1000 other applicants
to that job.
Even if you take your resume and run it through AI
and you match it to the job description perfectly,
there are still a thousand other applicants for that job.
So how do you set yourself apart from that?
You need to network,
you need to know maybe the hiring manager,
maybe somebody at the job, you need a reference.
You need all of those things.
And so, what I'd like to see students do more
is get out there and network.
How can you all help?
You can build communities at your colleges, you can build
or you can encourage folks to go to other communities,
go to other event or what have you.
- Yeah, I would absolutely agree with both comments.
I think too, there's a,
an opportunity to start to create some business awareness
and some context in kind of that student mindset, right?
So, what do I mean, right?
At the end of the day,
we're trying to secure data systems, network, et cetera,
but why, right?
Who are the teams? Who are the stakeholders?
Why does it matter? I still see that there's,
that's not always getting addressed.
And so, so technology's great,
it's important in having the functional skillset in that
is important, but a lot of times what I see in the workplace
is the inability to relay that context to the stakeholder
or to understand who the stakeholders are
and to try and find ways
to help create that balance of enablement
as well as control, which is,
a lot of times we focus on more the control side in security
and it creates, or, you know, it creates a divide.
And so, you know, I think that
that's one area that we can really focus on.
You know, I like to see a little bit more too on the OT, ICS
or industrial control system side too into a curriculum
because I think a lot of times we focused on more
the IT side of things.
And you know, we look at the critical infrastructure,
risks to critical infrastructure, investments.
We've come a long way.
Companies have started developing products and services
to help secure that space, but it still has a long way to go
when compared to the IT side of it.
So, being able to kind of bolster curriculum
or create curriculum around those areas,
I think will help create better rounded students.
And, and you know, you'll have the amplifiers of networking
and all the other,
you know, skills that they're getting in the curriculum.
- I'm very glad you talked about OT, absolutely lack.
So I was, at, last week I was at this FBI academy talk
and in which where I led a breakout discussion
and there was an OT person who
I guess I won't say with agency,
approached me and they said, there is nobody here from OT,
there's nobody applying to any of my positions,
there's nobody in this industry that I can hire.
So OT is an untapped industry that is,
you know, unsecured.
- [Person] What is OT? - Operational technology.
I was just gonna mention something.
What's what's interesting about our space too,
again, it's an unintentional process,
but we speak in code, right?
And so, that's part of,
unfortunately, that's part of how we gate keep too.
Yeah, it's unintentional. I apologize.
Don't mean to say it that way, but it's part of
when you're having those conversations in a room
and people are just like,
wow, you're all a part of the dark magic
and you know how to do the things.
And that's, I think that's the toughest part is one,
step one, understanding, put it on the table.
Cybersecurity is not an entry-level position.
Step two, nobody wants to hire an entry-level person.
Like, the joke in the space right now is
as a cybersecurity person is, you see, again, alphabet soup,
a CISSP for a position that pays about 60 grand a year.
What that relates to in education is a PhD
for a $60,000 a year job.
Right, so years of experience,
but that's where, that's where it gets tough
is those are the barriers that a lot of people
that are in the hiring space created for us.
And so by creating those barriers at the hiring level,
not truly understanding
and 'cause we're trying to get into these spaces,
a lot of the security folks trying to get into spaces
and the people that are hiring us
don't understand what it is that we do
because again, it's a dark magic.
And somebody within the space, somebody,
a consultant or someone built that requirement
for those roles.
And that's where it starts to get tough.
So making sure that students understand where the pathway is
through cybersecurity
or through to cybersecurity as the end goal,
I think really needs to be a part of the conversation.
And so that's, you know, from resume building to networking,
that's huge.
'Cause it is such a close knit community
that if you know someone,
you know someone, you know someone.
And having the ability to make sure that we're focusing
and getting our students to understand
that it's not just about getting a degree
or getting a check mark next to your name.
It's about making absolutely sure that
as you're given opportunities, you take them,
you network, you put yourself out there.
A friend of mine who works at Netflix made a joke of like,
oh, don't you, she was talking to my cybersecurity students.
She says, don't you guys go to meetups?
And I'm like, no, no, we're IT nerd, we stay home. You know?
And, but that's what's, that's what's missing
is a lack of getting out there
and making sure that it's not just a name or a degree
or a resume, it's a face and a person.
- Yeah, he knows I'm gonna say this,
but, in order to obtain a CISSP,
you have to have three years of experience.
So how does that even belong on an entry level position?
Right? So, yeah, he knew, I was gonna say.
So that's so frustrating to me when I see that on anything.
Just wanna like throw from this table.
Like he knows my frustration with that.
That's just a poorly written job description. And, you know?
- So I have a related question.
So most of us in the community college spaces,
at least my former college at Foothill College
and De Anza, where I'm at right now,
we offer cybersecurity programs,
which are maybe four or five classes,
which lead to a certificate in,
of completion in cybersecurity.
But clearly, what I'm hearing from you
is one needs much more than that
in order to be able to get into a job.
So that I see already as one major barrier.
And the other one that I've heard also, you talk about, is
you have to know someone
who knows someone who knows someone.
Our students don't know anybody.
They're all first time college goers for the most part.
And it is already a huge barrier for them
to come to college.
But beyond that,
and to have actual networking connections
is already a huge challenge.
So how are we gonna reconcile these two sort of big issues
that we have here?
- So that's a good follow up.
So, as I mentioned earlier, my colleague also mentioned
cybersecurity, as an entry job, is very hard
because if I, you know, I manager, I have a company,
I don't want to hire someone who is new,
and, as a cybersecurity specialist.
However, I have student ask me,
how do I even get into the field
and does the certification, you know, really helps?
Of course, it helps.
Because without a job related experience,
certification is only one that hiring manager will say,
well, you probably know something, right?
But another key things, as I told,
you know, the student who asked me,
I said, well, if you really wanna get into cybersecurity,
if you cannot get that job, don't worry.
That is not really the one you want to get right away
because you should, I also tell them,
go apply for help desk, help desk in any company,
many company have help desk job.
And the help desk from there, if you prove yourself,
it can be easy, migrated to a higher position,
help desk require you have a skill set
in basic knowledge that cybersecurity requires.
Whether it's already a system, programming,
you know, networking, everything, right?
So another since, you know,
that people mentioned about the student,
you know, you mentioned,
well, our student doesn't know anybody, which isn't true,
they know somebody,
you know, their professors or as they said,
maybe you should go out.
And so Aaron and I are involved
in a number of organizations.
Sometimes we have, you know, event we need volunteers.
I always encourage our students,
you have to go to the volunteers
because one of the event, we have a CIO scholarship fund,
we have an annual golf event,
and we have about a hundred senior high team, CIO, the CSO
over there at a golf course.
And in the past many years,
some students actually got internship right there
and they got a job offer
because they become a personal, right?
And so, you know, I use the word industry,
you know, sometimes some of the job is not advertised,
it's there.
And I write out job description afterwards.
Well, that's a fact of life, you know?
- I think there's another question,
sorry, I think there's another question
that I'll come back to this on.
But what I want to also mention here,
I mentioned some other, some other techniques,
but another technique is just to reach out
to folks from industry
and have them come in and guess lecture.
That's how I started with my involvement in this space,
in this educational space.
And then grow it from there.
So doing that could bring in
some semblance of networking for your students,
bringing in folks that are in industry.
You'd be surprised how many people just answer LinkedIn,
if you do that.
I have for security awareness programs with companies,
that's when you want the company
to become more security aware.
You want to build a culture of security awareness.
I've just reached out to authors,
so I sort of do the opposite, right?
I reach out to an author of a cybersecurity book and I say,
hey, will you come in and speak to the company?
So you'd be surprised, most of them, most of them do.
Now sometimes you have to buy their book,
but that's fine, right?
Just buy their book or whatever, right?
- I've got one, everyone's gonna cringe as soon as I say it.
Esports.
So if you didn't know, and there's only about,
I believe, five or six in the southern region,
there is a organization
called the Intercollegiate Cyber Defense Competition.
And it's an amazing program and it's an esport.
I joke with my wife,
I'm like, 'cause I'm not a sports person,
I'm like, I want to be a coach, a college coach,
that's the sport that I'm gonna go after.
It's an amazing opportunity.
I believe Coast, if you're, if anyone from Coast is here,
I think the last couple of years they've actually hosted
one of the events on their site.
It's a great opportunity for students
to get in front of industry, not just like need industry,
but get in front of industry, get into environments
where they're actually learning to do things
in an actual cyber range, is what we call them.
And so to be able to actually do things, touch things,
interact with other people, network,
it's an amazing program.
And again, it, it really ties back
to that college experience
that we have an opportunity to provide, so.
- Thank you.
So I think this is a nice segue
to the next question that I want to ask, which is,
can you share some examples, successful examples
of partnerships between community colleges and industry
that have led to meaningful student opportunities
like internships, apprenticeships,
or even maybe direct job placement?
So here's my question. I knew it was coming.
All right, so, I'll share a specific example.
Over the summer, this last summer,
so I teach a cybersecurity bootcamp once a year.
Over this last, over this last summer,
I met a student that was very interested in the field,
had the drive.
I invited him to my, my monthly event.
At that monthly event,
I introduced him to somebody that was hiring
and that person hired him on the spot, right?
Those things happen.
There are success stories like that that happened.
I was proud to do that and will continue to do that, right?
So. - Okay.
- Perfect, perfect example.
- All right, David.
- Yeah, I think I've seen some success
in some of the mentorship programs that some
universities and educational institutions are creating,
obviously, industry as well.
But, you know, being able to,
to kind of have that networking opportunity
to help guide students into whether it's,
you know, a professional organization
where they can start to build community,
whether it's, you know, a bootcamp or a cyber range,
it's really trying to teach that skill
of the interpersonal component and why it is important.
A lot of great comments about,
you know, it really is a differentiator
in the old adage, right?
It's, what, you know, but it's also who you know
and getting in front of people and helping them see that,
that sense of interest and ambition, curiosity,
absolutely agree to helping students
look at things through a different lens.
So sure, everyone wants to go straight to the top,
but, you know, there's a lot of value
in taking the necessary steps to build on that foundation
that you're getting from community college
or through other academic programs,
that's really, really vital.
And it's gonna help you reinforce those skills and expertise
and ultimately make them,
you know, successful in their career and their journey,
but also help that company that set out little caveat,
I wanted to mention a comment earlier,
but unfortunately, a lot of times corporations,
organizations are their own worst enemy,
that they don't really create a good ecosystem
or pathway internally
for that pipeline of students to come in.
You know, they're not necessarily doing great jobs
in supporting professional development
of their current employees.
You know, upward,
you know, lateral mobility in job descriptions
I find is lacking more than it's in place.
And so, you know, I think there's an opportunity for us
to start having conversations with industry and asking them,
you know, what is your succession plan?
What is your pipeline?
How are you, you know, supporting your current workforce,
but then also looking at, you know,
how to continue to replenish that workforce.
And, you know, a lot of times I see that still is a miss
that we can really start to have conversations around,
start to have partnerships around,
and create a lot more improvement.
- So I want to add on the student volunteers.
Well, I want to concentrate the word volunteers.
I have a student say, well, do you pay me for it?
Well, it's volunteer.
So it's an opportunity
the student has to take that advantage for.
So I have a perfect example, you know, two years ago,
I offered at one of our summer camp,
I have a student want to volunteer,
you know, I say I don't have money for it.
Volunteer? Yes.
So they volunteer for entire two weeks.
And after that, and I introduced to somebody I know
that he talked about the type of things he learned
at the summer camp,
how he helped other student and then the company hired him.
So, if a student say, I have to getting paid,
well, they're not really taking the opportunity
to try to help themself, not everything has to be paid.
It's your experience you need to get,
so you have to step out your, the comfort zone
and to help yourself.
- I think the other piece that has to happen too
is my personal networking,
and I'll talk about that piece of it.
So, my VP's in the back of the room,
who will know this, right?
So, I didn't see a pathway, so I built one.
Part of what we built through our security grant
was to make sure that we provided opportunities,
paid opportunities for our students
to actually come through
and then actually move into roles as opportunities.
And when I present to them,
I said, the gentleman from Palo Alto in the back,
I'll call you guys out,
plus other industry partners that I know.
I've got team, you know, members of Microsoft, CrowdStrike,
you know, name the big companies, right?
And so as I'm talking to them, it's not just about,
hey, you know, I'm potentially buying money
or spending money or working with you on something.
I'm like, hey, I have people coming into this space
and I would like to put them in front of you.
Where's that opportunity for me?
Where you programs,
'cause some of them have a lot of,
a lot of those big companies do have those opportunities.
But again, as we talked about it earlier,
it's who you know
and how do you get into those opportunities?
And so, for me it's also to make sure
that I'm networking myself to see who it is.
I think I was just on call with a big vendor the other day
and I'm like, hey, by the way, since we're here,
what do you do for internships?
And I actually had my two lead interns
who both happen to be female in the background listening.
And we talked about her history, her story,
how focused she was on bringing
especially females into site.
And, you know, that was a, it was an amazing opportunity
because now there's that connection.
So when something comes up for her, she's calling me.
And so, as a practitioner, as someone in the space,
as someone who's trying to do this for our students,
also about making sure I get out there
and I make those connections
to bring them back to the people that I'm trying to support.
- Thank you.
So, if you were all there at the main stage this morning,
we saw the chancellor from my district,
Lee Lambert, an AI generated video of him talking,
which was kind of fun,
but also a little bit scary at the same time.
So, we are talking about cybersecurity here.
So can you share your perspective
on how AI has impacted cybersecurity,
made it more something that we have to pay attention to
or has it helped battle combat cyber threats?
- That's gonna be a whole talk on this, on this right here.
- We have time.
- We have time?
- I'll jump in really quick.
So. I want to make sure
that we don't just talk about cyber, right?
Because it really,
knowing that everything feeds into cyber, right?
Knowing that the help desk and computer science,
those fields, AI is completely changing.
That whole landscape, you see all the,
if you live up in the Bay Area,
you know when the FAANG companies have their calling, right?
So FAANG, Facebook, Apple, Amazon, Netflix, and Google,
even though they're Alphabet now,
you know, when the call occurs, you see those in the news,
and you see that happen.
And a lot of times that is,
we're reducing workforce because of the efficiency of AI.
And so when you see a thousand people
onto that chopping block,
they're not in the workforce, right?
So in addition to all of the things that are,
that our AI is doing to improve efficiency,
it's impacting our ability to get into those spaces.
We talked about a bunch of computer science instructors
especially who are like,
oh, we don't let the students use AI.
And in talking to teams at Netflix,
they're like, we don't not use AI, you know?
And so as we push students into those spaces,
it's not just about understanding the impact of AI
or that you need to know, have the foundational knowledge
of the topic that you're studying.
It's about understanding how the tools are changing
on a daily basis.
You know, that's not even from
attack and defense standpoint,
that's just how this is going to impact your roles
in the world.
And so I think that's a big conversation
that really has to be had in the classroom of how,
especially in the technology space,
it's not just about whether it's going to happen,
it's you're walking into a space
that's already impacted by this.
And we need to be teaching those tools now
before we get there, okay.
- Yeah. So I'm gonna add, I'm gonna add to that and say
the adversaries that are attacking companies, government,
infrastructure, et cetera, are absolutely using AI.
They're getting faster in time to,
the time to compromise is getting faster.
And it's because of AI, the, however, the defense,
our defenses are getting faster because of AI as well.
Those are the positives,
the negatives from a talk,
again from the FBI talk, last week.
We had the CSO of philanthropic speak there
and what he was talking about
was how they no longer have SOC tier 1 analysts.
So typically your SOC tier 1 analyst
is your entry level position.
So they no longer have SOC tier 1 analyst
because they have replaced them with AI.
Now whether or not everybody's gonna do that
in the next five years remains to be seen,
but you could, you should expect that over,
let's say the next 10 years,
that position may be gone, period.
So, what do we do about that? What do we think about that?
My thought is that
we need to start thinking the next layer up for SOC analysts
or security engineers in general,
or just security in general.
I think security engineers tend to have a very narrow scope
of what it is that their job is.
And it's very, this is my, you know, technology's my job
and that's all I need to think about.
What I'd like to see more
are folks that are a little more well-rounded,
they understand the business more.
Because AI right now, doesn't do that.
It doesn't understand that this is a business,
this is a company, this is a educational institution,
it's a, you know, it's a water plant,
whatever it is, it only understands the context that's given
for now until AI becomes smarter than we are,
it understands the context that it's given.
And so, people need to sort of outthink AI, if you will.
It's a weird thing to say,
but that's what I think we need to start to teach students,
don't think so myopically about your field.
Think more business, think more broadly.
- Thank you. I'm glad you're bringing up the topic
about what we should be teaching our students
because that is one of the questions that I had
is looking ahead, like let's say five years,
what changes do you think we should,
based on the changes that we might expect
in the cybersecurity landscape,
what should community colleges be doing
to prepare our students for the future?
What are some new curricular innovations
that we should be working towards?
- Well, technology changes rapidly all the time.
We cannot keep up with it if we are just teaching,
as a faculty of school.
So one of the key things is how do you work
with practitioners in the industry, right?
The people who really in the real world is doing that.
And I'm sure many of the school you guys
have an advisory board, right?
Have the people that actually share
their real world experience and advise you
what kind of a curriculum you have.
And so, just like I work with my colleagues
and I also encourage them to teach as well
and to become adjunct faculties, you know?
So I have a number of friends now
they teach at the San Jose State, Cal State, East
are only, right? Different schools.
So by then working in our classroom
and share with the real world examples.
And also they can help us to create a new curriculum and,
so that we can getting ahead,
you know, as we all know, right?
To create a new course is not like today is you one to one
tomorrow is there,
it take about six to nine months, right?
So you have to think ahead.
And, so it is more of a, how can you create something
that align with the skillset demand in the industry
in the next couple years.
And by working with industry practitioners,
that's all you're gonna get.
- Thank you.
- So six years ago, if I would've asked you
what's the biggest data breach you remember?
Some of you may say Target,
you guys remember when Target got breach?
That was a big deal.
Now, if I ask you this morning,
what's the biggest data breach you remember
that's happened in the last week?
And you can probably think of at least six, right?
The landscape has changed completely and dramatically.
Like ever since COVID and I talk about,
when I talk to specifically to IT folks
in the education space, the gloves are off.
Back, pre-COVID schools and hospitals,
cities and counties, water,
they were doing the public good and you don't touch them.
And ever since then
they come to find out we all carry insurance
and we all are really terrible at cybersecurity,
so they're gonna come after us in that respect, right?
And so, to be able to sit here and prognostic,
and unfortunately, in five more years
what that's gonna happen,
it's, I, it's, I'd love to do that.
I'd probably be able to make a lot of money.
What we work on in our process
is what's happening right now.
How do we grow this process? How do we understand it?
It's one of the fun things I actually do with my students
is actually,
I require them to come in bringing current events
because remember doing current events
in like junior high and elementary school.
And so what we'll do is we'll walk through a data breach,
like just based off of what is, what did you read?
Who was it? What was the threat actor? What was the way in?
And that's what you are building,
is you're not building necessarily a person
who can kind of come in and look at screens that go by.
You're building someone who can think critically,
can understand organizational risk.
You're building that process of like wholly understanding
what an incident is and does.
And then how do we bring this tooling in to address it.
So, it really is a ch it's changing daily
and changing how we make sure we focus our students
and the people that are working in the space
to make sure that they're understanding
every single day something's happening.
- So you touched on a number of different things
that I want to, I don't know, emphasize.
One is, so I'm gonna hit again
on the ideal understanding business
like that that needs to be done
or at least understanding the greater organization.
If it's not business,
if it's, you're working on a water plant,
like understand why you're working on a water plant,
what the purpose the water plant is, right?
The other thing is risk.
And you touched on that, like thank you for that.
That's always gonna be true
regardless of technology, et cetera.
A fundamental understanding of risk and applying risk.
The greater the risk,
like maybe you shouldn't do the thing
regardless of technology.
I've said to a number of different executives
who just don't understand cybersecurity in general,
all cybersecurity is, is applying risk to technology.
That's all it is. That's all you need to think about it.
Just think about me as the chief risk officer
instead of the chief information security officer,
if that makes things easier for you.
And the other thing you had almost, Target.
So as somebody who worked at Albertsons',
we thought about Target a lot.
Here's a funny, a fun fact about Target.
One would've assumed, at least at the time,
that when that data breach happened
that it imploded Target like, or exploded Target,
like things would've just ended Target.
It affected their revenue for exactly three months.
And after those three months,
they went right back to normal, right?
But you know what didn't,
or you know what affected them more
was when they didn't have toilet paper on the shelves
in Target, Canada.
That closed the stores in Target, Canada.
They had a, they had to end up,
they end up shutting down those stores
because all of their customers went over to Walmart
who did have toilet paper, that's it.
Supply chain for them mattered more than anything else
because that's the risk for that business.
It's not people's personal data,
their credit card information, et cetera,
for that particular business, it's supply chain.
Because of the end of the day,
a physical product is what Target sell.
- And just to kind of add to that,
a lot of times I think we focus on threats
and call them risks,
really the risks is, is the business context, right?
And what resonates with the business leader
and helps us get funding, helps us,
you know, make certain decisions
that are gonna be either risk averse or risk tolerant.
So absolutely, plus point to all those.
The other thing I would say is,
you know, and we're slowly getting there
by changing the mental model
to more of a assumed breach, right?
The pendulum has shifted and the new normal is more attacks,
successful exploitation,
AI absolutely ramping up the ability
and lowering the bar for people to be able to do that
and do it at scale.
And so, you know, I think
again, we have to change how we think about things.
Zero trust is a great, you know, concept to help.
But, you know, there's still a lot of organizations,
a lot of people that have that kind of
crunchy outside, chew inside mentality of,
oh, we've got all these controls
and forget like what's the thing that's most important?
What's that data piece or what are the critical processes
that make this business run, and then work outwards.
And that'll help, you know,
really I think lessen some of the impacts,
at least, maybe hopefully the frequency of malicious events.
- Somebody wanna explain zero trust real quick?
- Go for it.
- Were there any questions form the audience?
Go ahead, Constantine.
- [Constantine] Yeah, this is,
so let's say a community college
establishes a cybersecurity lab.
I'm not an expert in it, I don't know the industry,
I don't know anybody, but we do care about our students,
and we do have students
who are really excellent in cybersecurity
and they want to go forward,
they have now the experience.
Internships are, I don't about internships,
but I'm not sure I know many people don't know internships.
What would you recommend?
I mean, I stopped by Palo Alto Networks,
I talked to the gentleman in the back, he's smiling.
And I said, hey, we got this Palo Alto,
this research plan we are establishing,
can you come over and talk to us
and see if we can partner and maybe teach them?
But is there anything in the industry or experts or how,
what would you recommend for us to go to the next step
so that we can bring these students
that do are very interested,
but they don't know what pathways to follow.
We do have a couple of instructors from your college here
that we teach those classes around, mention that,
but it stops there.
You take the class and then what?
So what would you recommend to get these students in our lab
as an internship, maybe with support from the industry?
Which industry? Palo Alto Networks? Somebody else?
How would you proceed?
- So, my partner in 909 Cyber
also struggled with this problem
and wanted to give back to the community.
So he decided he would do exactly that
and he started an effort called 909 IC.
Offline I can show you that website.
And so the idea there is exactly that.
Starting interns and get them connected with companies.
- [Constantine] Awesome.
- This is why I love working in community colleges.
Walk over to financial aid
and ask them about federal student aid workers, right?
And so, one of the things I'll ask students
that come to me and say, hey, I want a job.
I'm like, okay, hey first, you know, no,
don't answer the question.
I just wanna understand, do you receive aid?
Go to the FSA, go to the financial aid officer
and ask them if you have,
you're available for federal student aid
or the federal student work,
federal work student, excuse me.
- [Unison] Federal work study.
- The federal work study. Yeah, that is like right there.
I'll hire you right off off the rip.
Back when I used to run the help desk,
half my kids were federal work study students.
Because it's free, it gives opportunities for our students.
And that's one of the easiest ways, right?
The other piece of it too is look in work, right?
And again, it's dependent upon your own programs,
your own abilities within your districts
is how can we build this process within our own departments.
I'm trying to help guide that conversation
because, again, we can create those opportunities
as members of the department, as members of IT.
How do we provide those opportunities?
Look just outside the road,
did you ever know how understaffed and under capable
our K12s are?
We actually are, our internship programs goes out
and says, hey K12s,
would you like free students for the summer?
And that gives students the opportunity to go in,
wipe Chromebooks, plugin projectors,
you know, swap things out.
Yeah, it's, you know, it, it may or may not be paid.
Yeah, it may or may not be,
you know, super, you know, awesome.
But it's an opportunity, you know?
As he had mentioned earlier.
It's an opportunity to go out, to earn some time,
to show that you have a willingness
to work within this space.
So it's really a two sided process, right?
We internally, as the college
have to be willing to make those pathways.
And then two, the students have to be able to jump on
and run with us even though sometimes it may not,
it may not be paid.
- Look inwards. Just great advice, period.
- So I want to add some more,
I mentioned a little bit earlier,
community college student actually has a huge disadvantage
in the industry from internship.
You ask Palo Alto Networks.
They probably have some kind of school program,
but, you know, don't put you guys down.
You probably go to Stanford, go to UC Berkeley,
go to those named schools.
How many of you go to community college? Right?
It is hard.
Yeah, so maybe you can find out,
maybe you can start a community college programs
won't go back, right?
- [Person 2] I'm actually a graduate from community college.
- Okay. Yeah. That's even better, even better.
That's even better, right?
- And it comes from K12. - Yeah.
So, so it is hard.
So one of the things is more of in your program, right?
I think as a faculty
you need to also get involved in the industry consortium,
industry organizations
because there are more company than just Palo Alto Networks,
Cisco.
And those are smaller companies, they do have,
you know, programs or internship or jobs
that they perfectly sometime want to hire student.
And that's what we recommend.
You know, that's where I place number of our student
to those companies because, you know,
they just say, oh we need it, yeah, that's great.
Right? So that's one, right?
So I think that's a very important part of it.
I say it is. I'm sure you guys have edge on from industry.
And they have a network too. Ask them, right?
- Yeah. I just to add to that.
Absolutely, it's relationship management 101, right?
It's kinda what we've been saying multiple times.
Networking, connections, you know, finding creative ways.
At the end of the day,
that's really what this career is, right?
It's a lot of critical thinking, problem solving.
And so, you know, those are the types of, I think, mindsets
that are be most successful.
But, you know, a lot of times
organizations may not have the bandwidth
to sit down and really understand, hey we,
they know they've got a need that's not being met,
but they may not have the ability to think past that
just because there's so much noise
through firefighting constantly.
So, I think there's an opportunity for,
you know, education system to come to them
and say, hey, we want to partner with you,
we wanna understand what are your needs,
what are your products? Where are there gaps?
How can we, you know, take our current internship programs
that work for other organizations
or other areas in the industry and apply that so that,
you know, you're giving a solution to an organization.
They don't have to try and sit down,
figure out how are we gonna build this.
If you can kind of package that,
that will be really impactful for a lot of organizations
and really I think remove some of that barrier to entry.
- I think we have time for one more question.
Yes, go ahead.
- [Person 3] Yes I come from community college
and I would like to collaborate as well
as we are opening door,
which is opened our first open AI lab.
Last week and this week, thank you so much.
I appreciate that.
So by the way, I think that cybersecurity
sometimes is taken for granted.
I do am undergoing a tech program right now.
And so, I taught myself about cybersecurity.
I was so scared when I read the book
about zero day and the stops net,
which is like really like a, becoming like a digital weapon.
And so with that, risk management right now,
where are we with preparing ourselves
for the quantum technology?
Because the risk management for that technology
is really scary for now.
But, in that capacity,
I just wanna bring back to that reaching the gap
because we would like to kind of like educate ourselves,
like more with the risk management approach
because as an educator, sometimes like the teacher
before my class forgets to sign out
and I can just easily hack person.
So I think like even the industry
like open password for some and it's just like,
there's so much open doors like anyone can enter as of now.
And then this quantum technology, how the VP ready for that?
If as simple as like logging out
or getting a two factor authentication
is something that is not kind of like progressing sometimes.
- I think you set us up for a whole new conference topic,
but if you all want to answer very quickly.
- Really quick, cybersecurity is not a function,
it's a culture.
It's a very hard move to make
within the community college system, especially.
Especially within education, we talk about,
oh gosh, academic freedom, we talk about all the things.
And, you know, and I come from this space, right?
So understand that that's, you know, I hear those words,
but, I talk to my cyber folks all across the state and say,
if you walk out in the middle of quad or wherever
and ask a random faculty member
who your cybersecurity person is,
are they gonna have an answer?
And if the answer is no,
that's because you haven't built the culture.
You have to build that level of understanding, of knowing,
in my organization, they're gonna be like,
oh yeah, that's the guy that sends us scary emails.
So, you know, and that's fine.
I send scary emails, that's okay.
But building a culture of security
is more important than any framework,
any process that we can put into place
because it's all about making sure
that our users are empowered
and that we and you understand what the risks are.
- Yeah. And I'd add to that by saying
that the best way to build a culture
is to do it from their perspective, right?
You mentioned taking over their account,
but because they didn't log off, okay?
Now explain to them what you could have done,
take over their bank account, et cetera, right?
And then, oh, you know, now I'm personally affected, right?
So that helps to build a security culture.
- Yeah. I was gonna say, you know, we're all plus one HR,
you know, the culture at absolutely is super important,
understanding what the risk tolerance is.
'Cause not every organization or institution's
gonna have the same risk tolerance, right?
I think one of the great things about education
is it's more open, you know, academics,
you know, is designed for us to be creative,
and to question, and to learn and be, you know, curious.
But at the same time, you know, sometimes the,
there may be more room to improve the security,
but it's personalizing it, right?
It's understanding what is that risk tolerance,
what are the examples that you know,
real impacts could have.
Maybe it's not necessarily too like a whole,
you know, community college stakeholder role,
but perhaps maybe if there's quality work that's being done,
it's a little bit more sensitive
or, you know, a certain department within the school system
that's dealing with privacy,
you know, confidential personal information, right?
Like those are gonna be good places to start
'cause they're probably gonna have less of a risk tolerance.
And then you can use them as champions, right?
You build upon your successes.
A lot of times I think we focus on,
you know, the doom and gloom, the cybersecurity
and, you know, everything's so scary.
But, you know, there are a lot of wins too, right?
It's not just about, I can't say this, the incident,
it's, hey, you know, here's some success stories
that we don't do ourselves.
We often forget to beat our own drum
and highlight where those wins are
and leverage, you know, other people
'cause leading isn't just going somewhere,
bringing people with us, right?
So, the more we can get that ground swell
and help people work smarter, not harder,
and you know, understand, you know,
what some of the trade offs are, right?
You mentioned MFA, that's always a big one.
And pushback, oh, that's an extra step,
there's friction involved.
And there's some ways to do that with less friction.
But it's also under,
you know, trying to have that conversation with them
and figure out what are really their concerns
and then see if you can address the root cause
or find, you know,
find an acceptable level of risk that works.
Knowing that if something, when it's really,
when something happens, you already kind of set the stage
to hopefully be able to respond faster
and be able to start to shift, you always stay up,
but build security in earlier as a partner
as opposed to, you know, someone who's kind of coming in
after the fact to tell people that,
you know, they haven't been doing what they supposed to
and sometimes it's still their fault.
- And then I guess I'd say real quick
for the quantum part of your question.
It does sound scary, but the protections from quantum
are not unknown to many of us or to all of us.
So it sounds scary,
but I don't think right now, today,
there's much to worry about.
Other than don't rely on only encryption
for your own protection mechanism.
- 62 character passwords.
- Yeah.
- All right.
So for our community college educators, go ahead.
- [Person 4] Just one more, just one more.
For the corporate, as an cyber security officer,
I'll ask my favorite softball question,
what is the biggest cybersecurity risk a company has?
- You know I answered that already. It's people.
- [Person 4] Huge part is? - All the people.
- [Person 4] Right?
- I'm gonna argue on that one.
As a guy in the space, I will tell you,
and I tell districts this all the time.
Like, if you can be taken down soup to nuts
because they got a hold
of a short term employee's username and password,
we are not doing right by our organization, so,
I mean, yes, there's the risk, but at the same time to,
from a security perspective,
I'm gonna own that right there.
And so you will never hear me tell my employees
that they're at risk.
They're a part of the process.
And that's a culture change right there too.
And I appreciate you asking that question.
- Yeah, we don't tell them that.
- It's nothing.
- All right. To sort of wrap up our conversation.
So here's what I heard
for us folks in the community college space
is we teach our students critical thinking skills,
problem solving skills, networking,
and how to build relationships.
So those are,
seem like those types of themes keep coming up
in many different spaces,
and that is something that we need to be working on.
For our industry partners,
I want to say, please partner with the community colleges,
that is definitely an ask from us.
Maybe join our advisory boards whenever you can
or teach at our colleges,
as we do have part-time/adjunct teaching positions.
And then most importantly, get to know our students.
So you might actually find them very talented.
And so with that, I want to thank our panelists
and thank you all for being here.
(all applauding)
That brings our panel to a close. Thank you.
(people murmuring)